原视频名：Chang'e 5 Spacecraft Lands on The Moon and Returns Moon Rocks To Orbit
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/lwLPzU8H3HI
原视频发布日期：20201207
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here
你好 我是Scott Manley
and this is the view from the Chang'e 5 lander as it descended towards the moon.
这是嫦娥五号着陆器向月球下降时的景象
Now this image sequence is about one frame per second.
这个图像序列大约是每秒一帧
In fact there's it's even worse than that. They're skipped frames and things like that.
事实上 可能比这还糟 因为中间有点掉帧或者类似帧数不平均的情况
So I really wanted to have give you something better.
那么我真的很想给你看一些更好的东西
And so I actually spent some time taking up the frames cleaning them up
所以我花了一些时间把这些帧清理了一下
应该是 github.com/baowenbo/DAIN
and then running them through some fancy AI to produce this.
然后通过一些花哨的人工智能来进行处理
I'm actually quite proud of this in the end.
其实最后我对这个视频很自豪
So on the left you've got the reconstructed video sequence
左边是重构后的视频
and on the right you have sort of the ground track there.
右边的是类似地面轨迹的视频
So that large crater that's coming towards us is Rümker K.
所以那个朝我们走来的大陨石坑就是吕姆克K陨石坑
It's the only named crater along this route.
它是这条路线上唯一一个被命名的陨石坑
So this processing thing actually took a ridiculous amount of processing power.
那么 这个(补帧)处理过程实际上耗费了大量的处理能力
It took several hours on my brand spanking new RTX 3070 video card.
在我的全新RTX 3070显卡上花了几个小时才做好
So to get an idea or scale, those two large craters that are coming down
那么 为了让大家有个规模上的概念 即将落下的那两个大陨石坑
those are both about two kilometers wide
均为两公里宽
and of course spacecraft is skimming across the lunar surface at over a kilometer per second.
当然 航天器正以每秒一公里的速度掠过月球表面
It's in the process of slowing down and decelerating towards a landing spot.
它正向着着陆点减速
There's a mountain out there on the right
右边有座山脉
that just rise above the plain of the Ocean of Storms.
就在风暴洋的平原之上升起
That's about 10 kilometers long from left to right and about 500 meters high.
这座山脉左右长约10公里 高约500米
I should also mention that this thing is running at three times regular speed.
我还得提一下 这个视频的播放速度是实际速度的三倍
The whole descent takes a lot longer.
整个下降的时间要比播放视频长很多
That large crater we're about to pass is about two kilometers wide
我们即将经过的那个大坑大约有两公里宽
and when we pass it, we're about 15 kilometers from the landing site.
当我们经过它时 距离着陆点大约就有15公里了
The spacecraft is still moving at hundreds of meters per second
航天器仍以每秒数百米的速度前进
and it's at altitudes below that of a commercial aircraft.
而且它现在的高度低于民航飞机的高度
So what we're going to look for is there's a crater that's right in the middle
那么 我们要寻找的是画面中间的陨石坑
and that is going to be very close to our landing site.
这会非常接近我们的着陆点
Now as we get close to that crater you'll see there's a couple of smaller craters on the edge
那么当我们接近那个陨石坑时 你会发现在它边缘有几个较小的陨石坑
so the large crater is about 300 meters across.
那么大的陨石坑直径约300米
The two small craters on its edge are about 30 or 40 meters.
边缘的两个小陨石坑大约有30或40米直径
So we're just gonna pass slightly past that.
那么我们会略微经过那个陨石坑
Now the spacecraft is now orienting down to start looking for actual landing sites
那么航天器正在向下定位 开始寻找实际的着陆点
because of course this has entirely autonomous landing cycle.
当然是因为航天器有着完全自主的降落工作周期
It's going to look for terrain that will support a landing.
它要寻找能够支持降落的地形
That means it's going to try to avoid boulders and other stuff.
这意味着它要尽量避开巨石和其他东西
So the next time this crater comes into view you can see it now.
所以下一次当这个陨石坑出现在视野中的时候 也就是现在
You're going to start seeing rocks and things like that that it's avoiding.
你就能看到它要避开的岩石之类的东西
So it traverses across the surface this is going to the east by the way across the moon.
那么它向东穿过月球表面
And it finds a small cluster of three craters here.
它在这里发现了一组共三个陨石坑
Now that little triangle of three craters it's going to land in the middle off.
那么这三个组成三角形的陨石坑中间就是最终要着陆的地方
That's about 50 meters across.
那大约有50米宽
At this altitude I'm thinking that it's maybe 100 meters or less above the surface so 300 feet
我觉得这个高度大概是离地表100米左右 或者说300英尺
and yeah it picks a spot and descends down into it.
是的 它选择了一个目标着陆点 并进行了着陆
Now at this point the interpolation gets really glitchy
那么 到了这里 补帧的瑕疵变得很明显
so I just switch over to straight up showing the frames as they were produced.
那么我就直接换回了原画面
So that was this pretty spectacular landing.
那么这就是这次非常壮观的降落
Of course we didn't get to see it live in real time
当然 我们没能看到着陆的直播
because China isn't as courageous as say India or Israel when it comes to a risky moon landing.
因为在有风险的登月活动上 中国没有印度或以色列那样的勇气
So again this landing site is in the middle of the Ocean of Storms.
那么再说一下 这个着陆点是在风暴洋的中间
This is just to give you an idea of where it is
这就能让你了解它的位置
if you were to look at the moon from the northern hemisphere
如果你从北半球望月 就是这个位置
if you're from the southern hemisphere you have to flip it upside down.
如果是南半球 就得把它倒过来
And we know exactly where the spacecraft touched down
那么我们知道航天器确切的着陆地点了
because the lunar reconnaissance orbiter made a pass very soon afterwards
因为月球勘测轨道航天器之后很快就飞过了那里
and was able to take a photograph showing the spacecraft on the surface of the moon.
并拍到了一张显示航天器在月球表面的照片
So while the lander was taking some nice photos showing the surface
那么尽管着陆器有拍下一些月表的漂亮照片
its main task was of course to get samples of the surface.
但当然 它的主要任务是获取地表的样本
It had this 2 meter long drill which was comparable to previous drills that had been performed.
它的钻头长达2米 可以与之前采样过的航天器相匹敌
They also scooped material from the surface of the moon.
他们还从月球表面取样
They have a sample return container which I presume differentiates this material.
而我觉得在样品返回容器 应该会把这两种样品区分开的
What happens with this by the way is this is a core drill which means it's a hollow drill
顺便说一下 这是一个岩心钻 也就是一个空心钻
and there's like a lining around it.
而周围有一层内衬
钻取细节可以参考 zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/328147790
And they basically pull the core out wrapped in this lining.
基本上 他们是把岩芯拉出来 裹在这个内衬里
And then wrap that lining around a cylinder like is a cable of core material.
然后再把内衬缠绕封装在桶里 就像装有岩芯的电缆一样
Okay it's kind of hard to explain.
好吧 这有点难以解释
They did also release this panorama that was taken using the camera.
他们还发布了这张用相机拍摄的全景图
This is like some ridiculous resolution because it's made up of a bunch of different images.
这分辨率高得离谱 因为它是由一堆不同的图像组成的
One of the things I like about the Chinese imagery is that
我喜欢中国图像的一个原因是
the moon shows a lot more color than we ever saw in Apollo.
月球上的颜色比我们在阿波罗任务中看到的要丰富得多
So yeah I think that by the way is the mountain that I pointed out on the way down
那么 顺便说一下 我觉得 那座山就是我之前在下降段时指出过的
the one that's got a couple of peaks and 500 meters tall.
那里有几个高于500米的山峰
It's about 13 kilometers south by southwest of the landing site.
它在着陆点西南方向13公里处
I don't know enough about lunar geography to know if this has a name but I'm sure it does.
我对月球地理不了解 不知道它是否有名字 但我肯定它有
I think the lander only spent like a day on the surface before it had finished its operations
我想着陆器在地面上只呆了一天就结束了它的操作
and had loaded the sample return canister into the ascent vehicle.
并将样品返回罐装入上升器中
So the ascent vehicle uses rocket engine obviously to reach orbit
那么 上升器显然是用火箭发动机来入轨的
but initially it gets given a push by a spring to make sure it gets enough clearance
但最初会被弹簧推动 以确保它有足够的间距
and then it lights its motor and of course ascends towards space.
然后它再点燃发动机 之后当然就会进入太空
不用猜了，这是航天六院研制的3000N发动机，使用双组元推进剂，
其中燃料可能是单甲基肼，氧化剂可能是四氧化二氮或氮的混合氧化物-1(MMH/NTO或MON-1)，
同样是嫦娥五号轨道器，天问一号轨道器的主发动机
来源www.chinanews.com/gn/2020/11-24/9345768.shtml，
zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/165957414
Uses liquid propellant thrusters by the looks of things.
看上去使用的是液体推进剂发动机
I haven't actually figured out what kind of propellant it's used
我还没搞清楚它用的是什么推进剂
but it has multiple propellant tanks so it could be a bipropellant it could be a monopropellant.
但它有多个推进剂罐 所以可能是双组元推进剂 也可能是单组元推进剂
根据中国航天报，应该是近月点约15公里，远月点约180公里的交会对接初始轨道
来源9ifly.spacety.com/forum.php?mod=viewthread&tid=4587&page=58#pid782739
Either way I think it goes into initially a 15 by 200 kilometer orbit
不管怎样 我想它最初都会进入一个15公里x200公里的轨道
and the vehicle had goes into this orbit same orbital plane as the vehicle remaining in orbit
而航天器进入该轨道的轨道相位与留在轨道上的轨道器的相位相同
and once it gets there it deploys solar panels and deploys a microwave beacon.
一旦它到达那里 它就会部署太阳能板和一个微波信标
So that the other spacecraft can catch it and rendezvous with it in space.
这样轨道器就可以捕捉到它 并与它在太空中交会
Now this rendezvous is one of the big firsts of the mission
那么这个交会 是这次任务许多创举中的一个
because previously all the rendezvous in lunar orbit have been with crew on board the spacecraft.
因为之前所有的月球轨道交会都是由航天器上的乘员来进行的
This is entirely autonomous.
而这是完全自主的
The most distant autonomous rendezvous I believe is in geostationary orbit
(在此之前)最远的自主交会 我相信是在地球静止轨道上的
when the Mission Extension Vehicle extended the mission of a communication satellite.
也就是延长任务载具(MEV)延长了一个通信卫星的任务时间(就是延寿或者说续命)
So the orbiter has to locate the launch vehicle, approach it and dock with it
因此 轨道器必须找到上升器 靠近并与之对接
so they can transfer the material across.
这样他们就可以把材料转移过去
Now strictly speaking this isn't necessary for a lunar sample mission.
那么严格说来 (轨道交会对接)对月球采样任务并无必要
应该是苏联而不是俄罗斯
Russia demonstrated a direct ascent sample return
俄罗斯验证了一种直接返回式的采样任务
and clearly the technology is well within China's reach if they want to build the thing this way.
而如果中国想用这种方式来制造这个探测器的话 技术上显然是完全可以达到的
Instead I think they're deliberately doing it the hard way because they want to test the limits.
而我却认为他们是故意用困难的方式来实现这个任务 因为他们想测试极限
They want to test new technology.
他们想测试新技术
So here we see the view of the docking approaching from behind here.
那么在这里 我们看到了从后面接近对接的画面
And what it's looking for these three spokes these are the handlebars
那么上升器在寻找什么呢？是这三根辐条或者说车把一样的东西
详见 www.zhihu.com/question/433528314/answer/1612895296
that it's going to try and grab with its capture system here.
上升器将尝试用捕获系统(抱爪式对接机构)来抓住它
The core of that ascender by the way is very very small.
顺便说一下 上升器的核心部分非常小
It's a meter a few feet across and the vehicle masses 400 kilograms according to Chinese scientists.
根据中国科学家的说法 它有一米 也就是大概几英尺宽 航天器的质量为400公斤
That makes it probably
这使得它可能
the smallest vehicle to have ever lifted off from the planetoid spherical body and got into orbit.
是有史以来从小行星(类)球体上 升空并进入轨道的最小航天器
So yeah the capture system grabs these bars and positions them into their cradles.
那么是的 捕获系统会抓住这些杆子 并将其放在支架上
So the vehicle can then retract them together and make sure that the two spacecraft are mated
这样航天器就可以把它们收回在一起 确保两个航天器是固定的
that then allows the transfer of the sample canister into the re-entry capsule
然后 这样就允许将样品罐转移到返回器中
which is part was going to be carried by the return vehicle into an Earth-return trajectory.
整个样品罐的部分都会被返回器带走 并送入地球返回轨道
So this returned vehicle is very similar in shape to a Soyuz
那么这个返回器的外形与联盟号非常相似
and it has reaction control thrusters and the ability to control its descent through the atmosphere.
那么它有RCS推进器 以及在大气层中控制下降的能力
There is of course the hatch being closed behind it
当然还有就是 在这之后舱门被关上了
because they obviously have to protect this.
因为他们显然需要保护这个
And now the capsule's sealed, they can detach themselves from the orbit module.
而现在返回器密封好了 上升器就可以从轨道器中脱离出来
They actually lose the docking adapter as well for mass reasons.
为了减少质量 他们实际上也分离了对接适配器
So the orbiter spacecraft is going to head back to Earth
那么轨道器将返回地球
and we're going to have a sample return in a week or so.
而我们在一周左右 就会得到返回的样品
Until then I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
在那之前 我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]